Osip Mandelʹshtam Papers, 1900s-1970s (bulk 1914-1937 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Tristia: author's manuscripts and typescripts of poems published in Tristia collated items, each in individual envelope, description on covers (1922), undated; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  1. Eshche daleko asfodelei..., no. 93: author's manuscript, Alushta -- 2. Ia nauchilsia vam, blazhennye slova..., part II of no. 86 ( Solominka): author's manuscript3: I. Kogda, solominka, ne spish v ogromnoi spal'ne..., part I of no. 86 ( Solominka): author's draftII. Sobiralis' elliny voinoiu..., no. 70: author's draft, undated (on reverse of item I) -- 4. Kogda, solominka, ne spish v ogromnoi spal'ne..., part I of no. 86 ( Solominka): author's draft -- 5. Kogda ty ukhodish i telo lishitsia dushi..., stanzas 2 and 3 variants of stanzas 3 and 6 resp. of no. 119 ( Za to, chto ia ruki tvoi ne sumel uderzhat'): typescript -- 6. V raznogolositse devicheskogo khora..., no. 84: author's manuscript7. Na rozval'niakh, ulozhennykh solomoi..., no. 85: I. author's manuscript with correctionsII. author's manuscript (2 sheets), part of third stanza missing -- 8. Ne veria voskresenia chudu..., no. 90, as published in Apollon 1916 No 9-10 (slightly different from Tristia version): author's manuscript9. Kak pakhnut topolia -- my p'iany..., no. 191, not included in Tristia: I. author's manuscriptII. Liubliu Moskvu i vozdukh..., longer variant of no. 426: author's draft -- 10. Kak etikh pokryval i etogo ubora..., variant of no. 82: author's manuscript with corrections
- Grifel'naia oda ( Zvevda s zvezdoi -- moguchii styk...), no. 137: author's manuscripts and drafts collated in four envelopes (1923 March), undated; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  1. author's draft, part torn off2: I. 3 drafts of stanzas 1 and 2 on three sheetsII. author's manuscript of stanza 2 -- 3. drafts of stanzas 3-8 -- 4. complete final manuscript with corrections, title on cover in hand of N. Khardzhiev
- "Book of 1928", undated; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  Author's manuscripts and typescripts of poems included in 1928 volume, 7 envelopes containing collated items; 3 additional poems (1914 September-1925)
  1. I. Ia ne znaiu s kakikh por..., no. 131: 2 author's drafts on two sheets both: II. Ia po lesenke pristavnoi..., no. 132: author's draft (pencil); author's manuscript on obverse2: I. Kak tel'tse malen'koe krylyshkom..., no. 139: author's manuscriptII. Voina. Opiat' raznogolositsa..., variant of no. 197: handwritten by NMIII. Voina. Opiat' raznogolositsa..., variant of no. 197: typed final manuscript, title A nebo budushchim beremenno... crossed outIV. Voina. Opiat' raznogolositsa..., variant of no. 197 and 139, combines stanzas from both: stanzas of no. 197 in hand of NM, of no. 139 in hand of OM -- 3. Kontsert na vokzale ( Nel'zia dyshat', i tverd' kishit cherviami...), no. 125: author's manuscript, slightly different from published version -- 4. Nashedshii podkovu, no. 126: author's manuscript with corrections, beginning in hand of NM, on 2 sheets5: I. Synov'ia Aimona ( Prishli chetyre brata...), no. 461: opening fragment, in hand of NM, dictated by OM; on obverse of same sheetII. Gde rimskii sudiia sudil chuzhoi narod..., no. 39: typed copy, without title6. Vy, s kvadratnymi okoshkami..., no. 142: I. manuscript with corrections in hand of NMII. typescript with corrections in pencil, date in hand of NM7: I. Parizh ( Iazyk bulyzhnika...), slightly different version of no. 138: author's manuscript on obverse of sheetII. translation of Ulenspiegel Legend by Charles de Coster: typewritten fragmentIII. draft of telegram to Ia. Gorlin, in hand of OM -- 8. "Nozdri razduty kak kryl'ia...", variant of last two stanzas of no. 128 ( S rozovoi penoi ustalosti u miagkikh gub): author's manuscript with corrections -- 9. "Mne khochetsia bezhat' ot moego poroga..." fragment of 1 ianvaria 1924 ( Kto vremia tseloval v izmuchennoe temia...), no. 140: typescript10. Vek ( Vek moi, zver' moi, kto sumeet...), no. 135: I. author's manuscriptII. variant of last stanza ("I eshche nabukhnut pochki..."): draft in hand of OM 3 poems not included in 1928 book -- 11. Zhizn' upala, kak zarnitsa..., no. 198: copy in hand of NM12: I. Morozhenno. Solntse. Vozdushnyi biskvit... ( "Morozhenno!"), no. 63: author's manuscript, on top left corner in hand of OM: Nov[yi] Sat[irikon]. 1915. No 26; on obverse of same sheetII. Poliaki! Ia ne vizhu smysla... ( Poliakam), no. 176: copy in hand of S. P. Kablukov
- Neapolitanskie pesenki: translations of Neapolitan songs (1935 April-June), undated; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  1. 5 Neapolitan songs, no. 555: manuscripts with variants and corrections in hand of NM, each poem on separate sheet: I. Pravliu ia s chest'iu..II. Na povorotakh lodka poslushna.. III. Plavitsia v nebe..., IV. Ia snariazhaiu.. V. Ia probegaiu.. 2. Kanatella ( Umoliaiu, Kanatella...), no. 557: I. typed final manuscript, date in hand of NMII. manuscript with corrections in hand of NM -- 3. Nina iz Sorrento ( Na gulian'e v P'edikhotta), no. 556: typed final manuscript with corrections and additions in hand of NM (ink and pencil) -- 4. Skorei k oknu, krasavitsa!..., no. ?: manuscript with corrections in hand of NM
- "Vatikanskii spisok" ("Codex Vaticanus"), undated; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  Copies of OM's 1930-1935 poems made by NM in 1935, 8 envelopes, each contains several numbered pages of poems, pp. missing: 12, 23-24, part of 29-30, 31-32, 1. pp. 1-8 (1930-1935)
  1. pp. 1-8: I. Kuda kak strashno nam s toboi..., no. 202II. Ty rozu Gafiza kolyshesh..., no. 204III. Akh, nichego ia ne vizhu..., no. 296IV. Ty krasok sebe pozhelala..., no. 205V. Zakutav rot, kak vlazhnuiu rozu..., no. 207VI. Ruku platkom obmotai..., no. 178VII. Orushchikh kamnei gosudarstvo..., no. 179VIII. Ne razvaliny -- net..., no. 180IX. Kholodno roze v snegu..., 211X. Kakaia roskosh v nishchenskom selen'i..., no. 183XI. O porfirnye tsokaia granity..., no. 182XII. Lazur' da glina, glina da lazur'..., no. 215XIII. Ia tebia nikogda ne uvizhu..., no. 184XIV. Na politseiskoi bumage verzhe..., no. 189XV. Ne govori nikomu..., no. 201XVI. Koliuchaia rech araratskoi doliny..., no. 186XVII. Kak liub mne natugoi zhivushchii..., 217XVIII. Dikaia koshka armianskaia rech..., no. 218XIX. I po zverinomu voet liud'e... no. 220XX. Ia vernulsia v moi gorod, znakomyi do slez..., no. 221 verso: "Odin evrei, dolzhno byt'...," no.?: stanza in hand of NMXXI. S mirom derzhavnym ia byl lish rebiacheski sviazan..., no. 222XXII. My s toboi na kukhne posidim..., no. 224XXIII. Ia skazhu tebe s poslednei priamotoi..., no. 226XXIV. Za gremuchuiu doblest' griadushchikh vekov..., 197XXV. Koliut resnitsy. V grudi prikipela sleza.., no. 229XXVI. Zhil Aleksandr Gertsevich..., no. 228XXVII. Noch na dvore. Barskaia lzha... no. 204XXVIII. Net, ne spriatatsia mne ot velikoi mury..., no. 232XXIX. Ia s dymiashchei luchinoi vkhozhu... ( Nepravda), no. 231 (no title)XXX. Ia p'iu za voennye astry, za vse, chem korili menia..., no. 2332. pp. 9-11: I. Sokhrani moiu rech navsegda..., no. 235, Moscow, Starosadskii per.II. Neuzheli ia uvizhu zavtra? ( Kantsonna), no. 236III. Polnoch v Moskve. Roskoshno buddiiskoe leto..., no. 260[IV-VII: "Otryvki iz unichtozhennykh stikhov" (fragments of destroyed poems), 2 copies]IV. V god tridtsat' pervyi ot rozhden'ia veka..., no. 237V. Uzh ia liubliu moskovskie zakony..., no. 238VI. Zakhochesh zhit', togda gliadish s ulybkoi..., no. 239VII. Ia bol'she ne rebenok..., no. 240VIII. Dovol'no kuksit'sia! Bumagi v stol zasunem..., no. 2473. pp. 13-16: I. Segodnia mozhno sniat' dekal'komani..., no. 221II. Eshche daleko mne do patriarkha..., no. 251III. Tam, gde kupal'ni-bumagopriadil'ni..., no. 224IV. O, kak my liubim litsemerit'..., no. 253V. Lamark ( Byl starik, zastenchivyi, kak mal'chik...), no. 254VI. Kogda v dalekuiu Koreiu..., no. 255VII. Daite Tiutchevu strekozu..., no. 259VIII. "Kakoe leto! Molodykh rabochikh... ": last stanza of Segodnia mozhno sniat' dekal'komani... no. 221, later copy in hand of NM4. pp. 17-19: I. Vy pomnite, kak beguny..., no. 257, VoronezhII. "Uvy, rastaiala svecha...": last four stanzas of Novellino ( Vy pomnite, kak beguny...), no. 256III. Impressionizm ( Khudozhnik nam izobrazil...), no. 258IV-VI. Stikhi o russkoi poezii...: Siad', Derzhavin, razvalis'..., no. 233, undated Zashumela, zadrozhala..., no. 263, 1932 July 4 Poliubil ia les prekrasnyi..., no. 235, 1932 July 3-7VII. Batiushkov ( Slovno guliaka s volshebnoiu trost'iu...), no. 2615. pp. 20-22: I. Sebia gubia, sebe protivorecha..., 266II. Ne iskushai chuzhikh narechii, no postaraisia ikh zabyt'..., no. 240III. Ariost ( Vo vsei Italii priiatneishii, umneishii...), no. 267IV. Drug Ariosta, drug Petrarki, Tasso drug..., 269, Old Crimea, 1933 May Voronezh; 1935 August On reverse side: Ukrashalsia otbornoi sobachinoi..., no. 353: copy in hand of NM (blue ink), crossed out in pencil, undatedV. Ariost (V Evrope kholodno, v Italii temno...) 6. pp. 25-28: I. Liubliu poiavlenie tkani..., no. 275, Moscow, 1933 November, Voronezh, 1935 JulyII. Liubliu poiavlenie tkani.., variant, no. 276, MoscowIII. O, babochka, o, musul'manka..., no. 247, MoscowIV. Shestogo chuvstva kroshechnyi pridatok..., no. 278, MoscowV. Preodolev zatverzhennost' prirody..., no. 249, MoscowVI. Kogda, unichtozhiv nabrosok..., no. 250, MoscowVII. I Shubert na vode i Motsart v ptich'em game..., no. 281, MoscowVIII. I klena zubchataia lapa..., no. 282, MoscowIX. Skazhi mne, chertezhnik pustyni..., no. 253, MoscowX. V igol'chatykh chumnykh bokalakh..., no. 254, MoscowXI. I ia vykhozhu iz prostranstva..., no. 285, Moscow, fragment torn off, date missingXII. Kak iz odnoi vysokogornoi shcheli..., no. 256, Moscow, date corrected in pencilXIII. Reka, razbukhshaia ot slez solenykh..., no. 488, date corrected in pencilXIV. Kak solovei sirotstvuiushchii slavit..., no. 487, date corrected in pencilXV. Kogda usnet zemlia i zhar otpyshet..., no. 489, Moscow, date corrected in pencilXVI. Promchalis' dni moi, kak by olenei kosiashchii beg..., no. 490, Moscow date corrected in pencil 7. pp. 29-307. pp. 29-30: I. On dirizhiroval kavkazskimi gorami..., no. 262II. A posredi tolpy --zadumchivyi, bradatyi..., no. 290III. Masteritsa vinovatykh vzorov..., no. 2958. pp. 33-40: I. Ia zhivu na vazhnykh ogorodakh..., no. 304II. Naushnichki, naushniki moi!..., no. 268III. Pusti menia, otdai menia, Voronezh.. IV. Ia dolzhen zhit', khotia ia dvazhdy umer..., no. 305V. Chernozem ( Pereuvazhena, perecherna, vsia v khole...), no. 299VI. Mir nachinalsia strashen i velik..., no. 516VII. Mne kazhetsia, my govorit' dolzhny..., no. ?VIII. Da, ia lezhu v zemle, gubami shevelia..., no. 306IX. Eshche my zhizn'iu polny v polnoi mere..., no. 302X. Den' stoial o piati golovakh. Sploshnye piat' sutok..., no. 313XI. Ot syroi prostyni govoriashchaia..., no. 281XII. Rimskikh nochei polnovesnye slitki... no. 284XIII. Vozmozhna li zhenshchine mertvoi khvala?..., no. 314, last two lines corrected in pencil in hand of NMXIV. Na mertvykh resnitsakh Isaakii zamerz..., no. 315XV. Kak na Kame-reke glazu temno, kogda..., no. 308XVI. Ia smotrel, udaliaias' na khvoinyi vostok..., no. 310XVII-XXIII Stansy, no. 312 XVII. "Ia ne khochu sred' iunoshei teplichnykh..."XVIII. "Prokliatyi shov, nelepaia zateia..."XIX. "Podumaesh, kak v Cherdyne-golube..."XX. "I ty, Moskva, sestra moia, legka..."XXI. "Moia strana so mnoiu govorila..."XXII. "Ia dolzhen zhit', dysha i bol'sheveia..."XXIII. "I ne ograblen ia i ne nadlomlen..."XXIV. Bezhit volna, volnoi volne khrebet lomaia..., no. 319XXV. Ispolniu dymchatyi obriad..., no. 318XXVI. Za Paganini dlinnopalym..., no. 298XXVII. Ne muchnistoi babochkoiu beloi..., no. 288, Voronezh
- "Natashina kniga" ("Natasha's book"), undated; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  3 notebooks with copies of OM's poems 1930-1937 made by NM, Voronezh, 1926-37, most poems crossed out in pencil recorded later from memory (1930-1937)
  1. Iz-za domov, iz-za lesov..., no. 322, Voronezh -- 2. Kogda zaulybaetsia ditia..., first two stanzas of no. 342, crossed out in pencil -- 3. Moi shchegol, ia golovu zakinu..., no. 324, Voronezh, date corrected in pencil -- 4. Kogda shchegol v vozdushnoi sdobe..., no. 327, crossed out in pencil, note in margins -- "Recorded from memory in Voronezh after OM's death" -- 5. Nynche den' kakoi-to zheltorotyi..., no. 294, Voronezh -- 6. Ia v serdtse veka, put' neiasen..., no. 332, Voronezh -- 7. Ne u menia, ne u tebia -- u nikh..., no. 328, Voronezh -- 8. Vnutri gory bezdeistvuet kumir..., no. 330, Voronezh -- 9. A master pushechnogo tsekha..., no. 299, crossed out in pencil -- 10. Sosnovoi roshchitsy zakon..., no. 335, Voronezh -- 11. Plastinkoi tonen'koi zhilleta..., no. 334, Voronezh -- 12. Shlo tsepochkoi v temnovod'e..., no. 339, Voronezh, crossed out in pencil -- 13. Eta oblast' v temnovod'e..., no. 338 -- 14. Vekhi dal'nego oboza..., no. 340, Voronezh, pencil correction of one word by N. Khardzhiev, later note by NM stating that N. Khardzhiev's correction was unwarranted -- 15. Kak podarok zapozdalyi..., no. 336, Voronezh -- 16. Ottogo vse neudachi..., no. 337, Voronezh -- 17. Ulybnis', iagnenok gnevnyi, s rafaeleva kholsta..., no. no. 321, Voronezh -- 18. Tvoi zrachek v nebesnoi korke..., no. 345, Voronezh -- 19. Ia okolo Kol'tsova..., no. 343, Voronezh -- 20. Kogda v vetviakh ponurykh..., no. 344 Voronezh -- 21. Drozhzhi mira dorogie..., no. 347, Voronezh -- 22. Vlez besenok v mokroi sherstke..., no. 348, Voronezh -- 23. O, etot medlennyi odyshlivyi prostor..., no. 313, Voronezh -- 24. Chto delat' nam s ubitost'iu ravnin..., no. 350, Voronezh -- 25. V litso morozu ia gliazhu odin..., no. 349, Voronezh -- 26. Ne sravnivai: zhivushchii nesravnim..., no. 317, Voronezh, crossed out in pencil -- 27. Kak zemliu gde-nibud' nebesnyi kamen' budit..., no. 357, Voronezh -- 28. Ia nynche v pautine svetovoi..., no. 355, crossed out in pencil -- 29. Eshche ne umer ty, eshche ty ne odin..., no. 354, Voronezh, crossed out in pencil -- 30. Slyshu, slyshu rannii led..., no. 358 -- 31. Liubliu moroznoe dykhan'e..., no. 359, Voronezh -- 32. Kuda mne det'sia v etom ianvare?..., no. 360, Voronezh -- 33. Kak svetoteni muchennik Rembrandt..., no. 369, Voronezh -- 34. Razryvy kruglykh bukht i khriashch, i sineva..., no. 366, Voronezh -- 35. Gde sviazannyi i prigvozhdennyi ston?..., no. 356, Voronezh -- 36. Kak derevo i med' Favorskogo polet..., no. 369, Voronezh -- 37. Oboroniaet son moiu donskuiu son'..., no. 371, Voronezh -- 38. Vooruzhennyi zren'em uzkikh os..., no. 346, Voronezh -- 39. Poiu kogda gortan' syra, dusha -- sukha..., no. 327, Voronezh -- 40. Byli ochi ostree tochimoi kosy..., no. 368, Voronezh -- 41. Sred' narodnogo shuma i spekha..., no. 361, Voronezh, title Vniz po Kame in hand of N. Khardzhiev, poem crossed out in pencil -- 42. Eshche on pomnit bashmakov iznos..., no. 363, Voronezh -- 43. Ia v l'vinyi rov i v krepost' pogruzhen..., no. 370, Voronezh, correction by N. Khardzhiev, later note by NM restoring corrected words -- 44. Esli b menia nashi vragi vziali..., no. 372, Voronezh -- 45. Etot vozdukh pust' budet svidetelem..., 8 stanzas from first 4 parts of no. 437 ( Stikhi o neizvestnom soldate), Voronezh, crossed out in pencil -- 46. Ia moliu, kak zhalosti i milosti..., no. 373, Voronezh -- 47. Charli Chaplin ( Charli Chaplin vyshel iz kino...), no. 386, crossed out in pencil -- 48. Ia videl ozero, stoiavshee otvesno..., no. 374, Voronezh -- 49. Na doske malinovoi, chervonnoi..., no. 375, Voronezh50-65. Armeniia: 50. Ty rozu Gafiza kolyshesh..., no. 20451. Akh, nichego ia ne vizhu..., no. 29656. Ty krasok sebe pozhelala..., no. 20557. Zakutav rot, kak vlazhnuiu rozu..., no. 20758. Ruku platkom obmotai i v ventsenosnyi shipovnik..., no. 20859. Orushchikh kamnei gosudarstvo..., no. 20960. Ne razvaliny -- net!..., no. 18061. Kholodno roze v snegu..., 21162. Kakaia roskosh v nishchenskom selen'i..., no. 18363. O porfirnye tsokaia granity..., no. 21264. Ia tebia nikogda ne uvizhu..., no. 184, Tiflis, date probably refers to whole cycle65. Lazur', da glina! Glina, da lazur'!, no. 215 -- 66. Na politseiskoi bumage verzhe..., no. 219, T[iflis] -- 67. Ne govori nikomu..., no. 201, Tiflis -- 68. Koliuchaia rech araratskoi doliny..., no. 186, Tiflis -- 69. Kak liub mne natugoi zhivushchii..., 217, Tiflis -- 70. I po zverinomu voet liud'e..., no. 220, Tiflis -- 71. Dikaia koshka -- armianskaia rech..., no. 218, Tiflis -- 72. Ia vernulsia v moi gorod, znakomyi do slez..., no. 221, Leningrad -- 73. Pomogi, Gospod', etu noch prozhit'..., no. 223 -- 74. My s toboi na kukhne posidim..., no. 224, Leningrad -- 75. S mirom derzhavnym ia byl lish rebiacheski sviazan..., no. 222, Leningrad -- 76. Posle polunochi serdtse voruet..., no. 195, Moscow -- 77. Ia skazhu tebe s poslednei priamotoi..., no. 226, Moscow, Zoological Museum -- 78. Koliat resnitsy. V grudi prikipela sleza..., no. 229, Moscow -- 79. Za gremuchuiu doblest' griadushchikh vekov..., no. 197, Moscow, one stanza in margins crossed out in pencil -- 80. Noch na dvore. Barskaia lzha..., no. 230 Moscow -- 81. Net, ne spriatatsia mne ot velikoi mury..., no. 202, Moscow -- 82. Nepravda ( Ia s dymiashchei luchinoi vkhozhu...), no. 231, Moscow -- 83. Ia p'iu za voennye astry, za vse, chem korili menia..., no. 233 -- 84. Sokhrani moiu rech navsegda..., no. 235, Moscow -- 85. Kak parlament, zhuiushchii frondu..., no. 234 -- 86. Zhil Aleksandr Gertsevich..., no. 228, Moscow -- 87. Kantsona ( Neuzheli ia uvizhu zavtra...), no. 236, Moscow -- 88. Polnoch v Moskve. Roskoshno buddiiskoe leto..., no. 260, Moscow, two dates, one in pencil89-92. "Otryvki iz unichtozhennykh stikhov" (fragments of destroyed poems), Moscow, Starosadskii per: 89. V god tridtsat' pervyi ot rozhden'ia veka..., no. 23790. Uzh ia liubliu moskovskie zakony..., no. 23891. Zakhochesh zhit', togda gliadish s ulybkoi..., no. 23992. Ia bol'she ne rebenok..., no. 240 -- 93. Dovol'no kuksit'sia. Bumagi v stol zasunem..., no. 247 -- 94. Faetonshchik ( Na vysokom perevale...), no. 248, Moscow -- 95. Kak narodnaia gromada..., no. 249, Moscow -- 96. Segodnia mozhno sniat' dekal'komani..., no. 143, [Moscow], Iakimanka -- 97. Eshche daleko mne do patriarkha..., no. 251 -- 98. Ia k vorob'iam poidu i k reporteram..., no. 223 -- 99. Tam, gde kupalni, bumagopriadil'ni..., no. 224 -- 100. O, kak my liubim litsemerit'..., no. 253 -- 101. Lamark ( Byl starik, zastenchivyi, kak mal'chik), no. 254 -- 102. Kogda v dalekuiu Koreiu..., no. 255 -- 103. Daite Tiutchevu strekozu..., no. 259 -- 104. "Uzh eti mne govoruny...", stanza 3 of no. 256 ( Novellino) -- 105. "Uvy, rastaiala svecha...", last four stanzas of no. 256 ( Novellino ( Vy pomnite, kak beguny...), Moscow -- 106. Vy pomnite, kak beguny..., no. 257, later note by NM: "Recorded from memory, hence mistakes...", Moscow, 1932 MayVoronezh, 1926 September -- 107. Khudozhnik nam izobrazil..., no. 258, Moscow -- 108. Batiushkov ( Slovno guliaka s volshebnoiu trost'iu...), no. 261, Moscow109-111. Stikhi o russkoi poezii: 109. Siad', Derzhavin, razvalis'..., no. 262110. Zashumela, zadrozhala..., no. 263111. Poliubil ia les prekrasnyi... no. 235, Moscow, date probably refers to all three poems -- 112. K nemetskoi rechi... ( Sebia gubia, sebe protivorecha...), 266 -- 113. Kholodnaia vesna..., no. 241, Staryi Krym, two new dates written over original one in different color ink, both crossed out in pencil, (, ) -- 114. Ne iskushai chuzhikh narechii..., no. 270, Staryi Krym -- 115. Ariost I ( Vo vsei Italii priiatneishii, umneishii...), no. 267, Staryi Krym -- 116. Drug Ariosta, drug Petrarki, Tasso drug..., no. 269, Staryi Krym -- 117. Ariost II ( V Evrope kholodno, v Italii temno...), no. 268, Staryi Krym, 1933 Voronezh, 1935118-128. Vos'mistishia: 118. Liubliu poiavlenie tkani..., no. 275119. Liubliu poiavlenie tkani..., variant, no. 276, Moscow120. O, babochka, o, musul'manka..., no. 277121. Shestogo chuvstva kroshechnyi pridatok..., no. 248122. Preodolev zatverzhennost' prirody..., no. 279, Moscow123. Kogda, unichtozhiv nabrosok..., no. 250124. I Shubert na vode, i Motsart v ptich'em game..., no. 281125. I klena zubchataia lapa..., no. 282126. Skazhi mne, chertezhnik pustyni..., no. 283127. I ia vykhozhu iz prostranstva..., no. 285128. V igol'chatykh chumnykh bokalakh..., no. 254 -- 129. U nashei sviatoi molodezhi..., no. 274 -- 130. Tatary, uzbeki i nentsy..., no. 273 -- 131. Kvartira ( Kvartira tikha, kak bumaga...), no. 272 -- 132. Reka, razbukhshaia ot slez solenykh..., no. 488 -- 133. Kak solovei sirotstvuiushchii slavit..., no. 487 -- 134. Kogda usnet zemlia i zhar otpyshet..., no. 489 -- 135. Promchalis' dni moi, kak by olenei..., no. 490 -- 136. Kak iz odnoi vysokogornoi shcheli..., no. 287 -- 137. Golubye glaza i goriachaia lobnaia kost'..., no. 288 -- 138. 10 ianvaria 1934 ( Menia presleduiut dve-tri sluchainykh frazy...), no. 289 -- 139. On dirizhiroval kavkazskimi gorami..., no. 293, crossed out in ink -- 140. A posredi tolpy zadumchivyi, bradatyi..., no. 290, Moscow -- 141. Kogda dushe i toropkoi, i robkoi.. -- 142. Otkuda privezli? Kogo? Kotoryi umer?... ( Belomu), no. 263 -- 143. Masteritsa vinovatykh vzorov..., no. 295
- "Al'bom no. 1", undated; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  Copies of OM's poems (various periods) made by NM in Voronezh in OM's lifetime and given to M. Iartseva in Kiev, returned to NM in 1959; page of "Al'bom no. 1" with Stikhi o neizvestnom soldate and 6 other poems was moved by I. Semenko to the rest of material for that poem (Box 2, Folder 23, item 104) (1933-1937 March 6)
  1-62. "Voronezhskie stikhi" ("Voronezh poems"): 1. Chernozem ( Pereuvazhena, perecherna, vsia v khole... ), no. 299, fragment torn off2. Ia zhivu na vazhnykh ogorodakh..., no. 3043. Ia dolzhen zhit', khotia ia dvazhdy umer..., no. 305, last line added in pencil4. Naushnichki, naushniki moi..., no. 3005. Pusti menia, otdai menia, Voronezh.. 6. Kak na Kame-reke glazu temno, kogda..., no. 3087. Kak na Kame-reke glazu temno, kogda..., no. 3098. Ia smotrel, udaliaias' na khvoinyi vostok..., no. 3109. Stansy, no. 312: "Ia ne khochu sred' iunoshei teplichnykh...", "Liubliu shinel' krasnoarmeiskoi skladki: stanza 2 of no. 312 (1), "Podumaesh, kak v Cherdyne-golube...", "Moia strana so mnoiu govorila...", "I ty, Moskva, sestra moia, legka...", "Ia dolzhen zhit', dysha i bol'sheveia...": variant of first two lines, crossed out, "Nelepyi shov, bezumnaia zateia..." first line corrected in pencil10. Bezhit volna, volnoi volne khrebet lomaia..., no. 31911. Ne muchnistoi babochkoiu beloi..., no. 32012. Vozmozhna li zhenshchine mertvoi kvala?..., no. 31413. Rimskikh nochei polnovesnye slitki..., no. 316undated14. "Ia dolzhen zhit', dysha i bol'sheveia...: Stansy, no. 312 (6)15. Den' stoial o piati golovakh..., no. 31316. Ot syroi prostyni govoriashchaia..., no. 31117. Ispolniu dymchatyi obriad..., no. 31818. Eshche my zhizn'iu polny v vysshei mere..., no. 30219. Plastinkoi tonen'koi zhilleta..., no. 33420. Eta oblast' v temnovod'e..., no. 33821. Vekhi dal'nego oboza..., no. 34022. Kak podarok zapozdalyi..., no. 33623. Ottogo vse neudachi..., no. 33724. Ulybnis', iagnenok gnevnyi, s rafaeleva kholsta..., no. no. 32125. Tvoi zrachok v nebesnoi korke..., no. 34526. Ia okolo Kol'tsova..., no. 34327. Kogda v vetviakh ponurykh..., no. 344: fragment torn off28. Drozhzhi mira dorogie..., no. 34729. Vlez besenok v mokroi sherstke..., no. 34830. V litso morozu ia gliazhu odin..., no. 34931. Chto delat' nam s ubitost'iu ravnin..., no. 35032. O, etot medlennyi, odyshlivyi prostor..., no. 31333. Ne sravnivai: zhivushchii nesravnim..., no. 31734. Kak zemliu gde-nibud' opal'nyi kamen' budit..., no. 35735. Kuda mne det'sia v etom ianvare?..., no. 36036. Slyshu, slyshu rannii led..., no. 35837. Kak derevo i med' -- Favorskogo polet..., no. 36938. Ia nynche v pautine svetovoi..., no. 35539. Gde sviazannyi i prigvozhdennyi ston..., no. 35640. Poiu, kogda gortan' syra, dusha sukha..., no. 32741. Byli ochi ostree tochimoi kosy..., no. 36842. Razryvy kruglykh bukht i khriashch i sineva..., no. 36643. Vooruzhennyi zren'em uzkikh os..., no. 34644. Sred' narodnogo shuma i spekha..., no. 36145. Eshche on pomnit bashmakov iznos..., no. 36346. Kak svetoteni muchennik Rembrandt..., no. 36947. Eshche ne umer ty, eshche ty ne odin..., no. 35448. Liubliu moroznoe dykhan'e..., no. 35949. Ia v l'vinyi rov i v krepost' pogruzhen..., no. 37050. Na doske malinovoi, chervonnoi..., no. 37551. Ia videl ozero, stoiavshee otvesno..., no. 37952. Ia proshu, kak zhalosti i milosti..., no. 37353. Nynche den' kakoi-to zheltorotyi..., no. 29454. Kogda shchegol v vozdushnoi sdobe..., no. 32755. Vnutri gory bezdeistvuet kumir..., no. 33056. Ne u menia, ne u tebia -- u nikh..., no. 32857. Ia v serdtse veka. Put' neiasen..., no. 33258. Sosnovoi roshchitsy zakon..., no. 33559. Za Paganini dlinnopalym..., no. 29860. Iz-za domov, iz-za lesov..., no. 32261. Kogda zaulybaetsia ditia..., no. 34262. Moi shchegol, ia golovu zakinu..., no. 32463. Drug Ariosta, drug Petrarki, Tasso drug..., 269, Crimea64. Ne iskushai chuzhikh narechii, no postaraisia ikh zabyt'..., no. 24065-69. Vos'mistishia: 65. Kogda unichtozhiv nabrosok..., no. 28066. Liubliu poiavlenie tkani..., no. 27567. Liubliu poiavlenie tkani..., no. 27668. I klena zubchataia lapa..., no. 28269. O babochka, o, musul'manka..., no. 27770. Daite Tiutchevu strekozu..., no. 25971. Vy pomnite, kak beguny..., no. 25772. "Uvy, rastaiala svecha...": last four stanzas of no. 256 ( Vy pomnite, kak beguny...)73. Khudozhnik nam izobrazil..., no. 25874. Kogda v dalekuiu Koreiu..., no. 25575. Kogda dushe i toropkoi i zybkoi..., no. 29176. Emu kavkazskie krichali gory..., no. 29277. On dirizhiroval kavkazskimi gorami..., no. 29378. Otkuda privezli? Kogo? Kotoryi umer?..., no. 26379. Golubye glaza i goriashchaia lobnaia kost'..., no. 28880. Menia presleduiut dve-tri sluchainykh frazy..., no. 289